<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>jmodigital.com/</title>
   
   <link>http://jmodigital.com</link>
   <description>A network of training clinicians interested in digital health and entrepreneurship</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Martin Seneviratne</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Automating primary care - tricks and tricorders</title>
	  <link>//automating-primary-care</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-05-12T20:00:00+10:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//automating-primary-care</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
<p>The Tricorder Prize has chanelled the imagination of med-tech entrepreneurs towards building an all-in-one diagnostic toolkit to fit in the palm of a hand. These devices stand to be an ally rather than a competitor for general practice. Their utility will be not so much in spot diagnoses as in longitudinal tracking of chronic diseases, offering intelligent, personalised advice to patients in between GP visits. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Tricorder X-Prize is an international innovation challenge promising US$10 million to the team who can crack the elegantly elusive problem of the &#39;tricorder&#39;. The tricorder is a device plucked from the realms of science fiction - a handheld health analyser originally featured in Star Trek which has the tri-functionality of <em>sensing, computing and recording</em> health. A little black box with a screen and detachable probe, the tricorder could sense vital signs, analyse bloodwork and thereby diagnose a range of medical conditions. Although it was able to send distress signals, the tricorder could not deliver treatment - it was a portable, easy-to-use diagnostic toolkit. </p>

<p>Almost 50 years after this device appeared on television screens, the med-tech community has pounced upon it as a legitimate scientific goal. The $10m X-Prize was announced in 2011 and 7 teams are now in the running, with the winner to be announced in early 2017. The criteria have been laid down - the device must be able to diagnose the following 10 so-called &#39;Core Conditions&#39;:</p>

<ul>
<li>Anemia</li>
<li>UTI</li>
<li>Diabetes</li>
<li>Atrial fibrillation</li>
<li>Obstructive sleep apnoea</li>
<li>COPD</li>
<li>Pneumonia</li>
<li>Otitis media</li>
<li>Leukocytosis</li>
<li>Absence of core conditions</li>
</ul>

<p>The 10th core condition - the absence of the other other 9 - is perhaps the most treacherous of them all if you read the fine print of the prize <a href="http://tricorder.xprize.org/about/guidelines">guidelines</a>. The gold standard that devices are held against to prove this null hypothesis is a very thorough workup indeed - test subjects undergo bloods, ECG, CXR, lung function tests, sleep apnoea tests and a brain MRI!</p>

<p>Incidentally, this list is actually a less ambitious version of what was proposed in 2011 when the prize first launched. There were originally 3 further conditions required: hepatitis A, tuberculosis and stroke. For bonus points, there is also an extra set of 12 &#39;elective conditions&#39; to grapple with including pertussis, hyperthyroidism and HIV.</p>

<p>Devices must also be able to record 5 vital signs (blood pressure, HR and variability, temperature, respiratory rate and oxygen saturations), with a push towards continuous monitoring and upload to cloud storage. </p>

<p>The 7 teams who remain in the running include 4 from the US and one each from Taiwan, Canada and India. The Canadian team <a href="http://www.clouddx.com/">CloudDx</a> have put forward the VITALITI platform - an app-based analytics tool that syncs with multiple sensors including a wireless otoscope and a microphone for analysing breath sounds. VITALITI also has brightly-coloured test sticks for samples of finger-prick blood, urine and saliva. </p>

<p><img src="http://www.clouddx.com/img/vitaliti_system.jpg" alt="VITALITI platform" title="VITALITI platform"></p>

<p><a href="https://www.scanadu.com/">Scanadu</a>, based out of the NASA Ames Research Center in Silicon Valley, have already gone to market with an early prototype, the Scanadu Scout, which will detect vital signs and provide basic recommendations for US$199.  They are now developing more sophisticated consumer health trackers called Scanadu Vitals and Scanadu Urine. Intriguingly, they already publish large-scale deidentified data through their <a href="https://www.scanadu.com/globalbodymap/">Global Body Map</a>, foreshadowing the potential for real-time population analytics of health metrics. </p>

<p><img src="https://tctechcrunch2011.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/scanadu-scout.jpg" alt="Scanadu Scout" title="Scanadu Scout"></p>

<p>Then there is Boston&#39;s <a href="http://www.dnamedinstitute.com/">DMI</a> team (DNA Medicine Institute), supported by the NIH and the Gates Foundation. They recently took out the smaller <a href="http://sensing.xprize.org/">Nokia Sensing X Prize</a> with their rHEALTH device - a miniaturised pathology lab able to perform 22 tests on a single drop of blood using microfluidics and laser spectrometry.</p>

<p>Victory will be in the detail, but the skeleton of these ideas has already been sketched out. All of them involve a range of wireless sensing devices for vital signs and laboratory testing, linked to a software platform that recognizes trends and provides a diagnostic prediction.   </p>

<p>As these teams converge on an elegant solution, the question we have to grapple with is this: how would a tricorder-style diagnostic device actually interface with the delivery of healthcare? After all, it only solves one half of the equation: identifying a problem but not initiating treatment. One could argue that if you have diagnosed a UTI, taking the next step and suggesting appropriate antibiotic therapy for an uncomplicated patient is not a huge technical leap. But patients are rarely uncomplicated. And even if there are no objective medical complications, the psychosocial intricacies of healthcare mean that general practice and sensor technology will have to work hand in hand. </p>

<p>This may not be such an odd coupling as some commentators, who prophesy the end of primary care with technological innovation, would have us believe. On the contrary, sensing technology might actually be the most useful tool for general practitioners in bringing efficiency to an increasingly overburdened primary healthcare system. </p>

<p>Let&#39;s consider the most frequent presentations in a GP clinic. <a href="http://www.racgp.org.au/afp/2013/januaryfebruary/common-general-practice-presentations/">Cooke <em>et al.</em></a> analysed almost 200,000 patient encounters from 2009-2010 using data from the <a href="http://sydney.edu.au/medicine/fmrc/beach/">BEACH program</a> to produce a list of the problems most frequency managed by general practitioners. Numbers 1-10 were: </p>

<ol>
<li>Hypertension</li>
<li>Immunisations/vaccinations</li>
<li>Acute upper respiratory tract infection</li>
<li>Depression</li>
<li>Diabetes</li>
<li>Lipid disorders</li>
<li>General checkup</li>
<li>Osteoarthritis</li>
<li>Back pain</li>
<li>Prescription refilling</li>
</ol>

<p>This list is notably different from the Tricorder Prize&#39;s top-ten list of acute conditions. The only item on this list that would typically require a tricorder-style spot diagnosis would be acute upper respiratory tract infection. (<em>NB. Although it may be possible to diagnose a large majority of URTIs based on a history of coryzal symptoms and certain relevant negatives, a rigorous diagnosis would also mandate examination of the pharynx, lymph nodes, conjunctiva, ear canals and breath sounds which is more difficult (although not impossible) to replicate with machines.</em>)</p>

<p>Apart from URTIs, almost all the other presentations relate to management of chronic conditions (with the exception of immunisations and general checkups). So the question of automating primary care is really one of automating chronic disease management. This is actually a domain where user-driven health tracking stands to be extremely useful. </p>

<p>Imagine if the GP&#39;s decision about anti-hypertensive medications was informed by an accurate day-by-day trace of a patient&#39;s blood pressure over the last month, along with medication compliance, exercise levels and heart rate. We then move from trial-and-error medicine to tailored therapy. Imagine if the management of diabetes was informed by detailed BSL tracking, HbA1c levels and urine dipstick tests performed in a patient&#39;s home. Imagine if analgesia for chronic back pain was titrated in real time based on pain scores and side effect profile, just as it is for hospital inpatients. Imagine if cholesterol checks could be done in the household and subjects triaged to physicians accordingly. Primary care would be all the richer for it!</p>

<p>At the very minimum, these sensing platforms could make primary care decision-making asynchronous: rather than a patient physically attending the GP, browsing through tattered copies of Women&#39;s Weekly in the waiting-room, sitting face-to-face and leaving with some advice, that same advice could be delivered electronically via a GP who reviews the health data at a time that suits them. </p>

<p>However we can go one step further. The picture that is really taking shape is of an automated concierge for chronic disease management in the home, advising on medications and lifestyle modifications in real time between visits to the GP. Of the 10 most common GP-managed problems, almost all could be tracked in a semi-automated fashion with the kind of devices competing for the Tricorder Prize.  </p>

<p>Primary care should not see these technologies as a rival, but as an ally. We are now at a critical fork in the road where we can build an ecosystem (including the regulatory and billing structures) to cater for semi-automated community medicine. And where private enterprises will be vying to get the automation right. As a medical profession, we should embrace these technologies and make them work for us, integrate them into our practice and let them extend our capacities, rather than undermine them as robotic competitors. </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Innovations in healthcare - lessons from the private sector</title>
	  <link>//innovations-in-healthcare-part-1</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-05-01T20:00:00+10:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//innovations-in-healthcare-part-1</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
<p>Innovations in healthcare are in high demand, and with good reason. Our new editor <strong>Rahul Gokarn</strong> discusses in this 3 part series.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Last week, Harvard Business Review (HBR) posted an article on <strong><a href="https://hbr.org/2016/04/making-predictive-analytics-a-routine-part-of-patient-care">using predictive analytics in patient care</a></strong>, Bloomberg discussed how <strong><a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/2016-04-20/2015-was-record-year-for-health-care-deals">2015 was a record year for health-care deals</a></strong>, and Forbes released two articles on <strong><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/theapothecary/2016/04/13/digital-health-funding-defies-expectations/#35459e147bb5">digital health funding</a></strong> and <strong><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/paullamkin/2016/04/26/nokia-moves-into-digital-health-buying-withings-for-e170-million/#77e566044275">Nokia&#39;s move into digital health</a></strong>.</p>

<p>With so much growth in the healthcare sector, particularly in digital health and tech investing, the search for innovation is clearly in high demand, and with good reason. The evolving challenges faced across the world in terms of ageing population bases, growing demand for access to quality healthcare, and rising costs associated with producing and distributing medications is creating a shift in sources of growth away from traditional organisations such as universities and hospitals, towards the private sector, where the majority of innovation, and investment is coming from.</p>

<p><img src="https://cbi-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Digital-Health-Deals-and-Dollars-1.7.20164.png" alt="alt text">
<sub>Image sourced from <a href="https://www.cbinsights.com/blog/digital-health-funding-2015/">CBInsights</a>[1].</sub></p>

<p>For many of us working in healthcare, it is clear that innovations in digital health and technology have the potential to provide massive improvements not only to patient care, but also in improving efficiency and reducing redundancies faced by modern systems and practitioners. While this need for change is unequivocal, and most, if not all of us have ideas for improvement, it is easy to simply focus on the circadian cycles of working life and neglect the most important aspect of change – implementation. </p>

<p>This is because innovation is much more complicated than just having an idea; initiating changes in healthcare can require a great deal of time and commitment, and more often than not, run into problems such as policy and regulatory issues, especially in large, well established systems like hospitals. Problems such as these have led to sluggish progress in the public sector, while the main sources of growth have been shifted to the private sector (big pharma, large scale tech companies such as Google, Apple, and IBM, healthcare startups, etc.) – but why is this the case?</p>

<p>Perhaps the chief reason for this is the lack of entrepreneurial culture bred into the public healthcare system. The intolerance for failure, lack of funding, and high level of regulation has led many to simply accept the current system rather than face the challenges associated with implementing change. This is not a new problem, and in fact, this articlefrom the HBR archives in 2006 describes <strong><a href="https://hbr.org/2006/05/why-innovation-in-health-care-is-so-hard">why innovation is so difficult in healthcare</a></strong>, and outlines 6 forces that influence the success or failure of innovative ideas. What is interesting here is that these factors are not specific to health, but can be applied to a variety of industries and businesses, and perhaps this is why there has been such a push towards innovation coming out of the private sector, where issues such as lack of funding and policy are often avoided.</p>

<p>What large public healthcare organisations are begining to understand is that in order to improve their systems, it is important to look for <em>innovative</em> solutions/technologies, rather than simply reallocate existing resources, or applying minor, incremental changes that rarely create meaningful change. In this way, healthcare organisations around the world, RPAH included, are taking lessons from the private sector and forming innovation committees to address these issues.</p>

<hr>

<p><em>For more information on any of the linked articles, or if you are interested in getting involved with JMO Digital or an innovations committee, please contact</em> <strong><em><a href="mailto:editor@jmodigital.com">editor@jmodigital.com</a></em></strong>.</p>

<p><sub>[1] We in no way claim ownership/credit for the data presented in the above image - source: <a href="https://www.cbinsights.com/blog/digital-health-funding-2015/">CBInsights</a>.</sub></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>What if hospitals were run by Apple</title>
	  <link>//what-if-hospitals-ran-like-apple</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-02-01T21:18:00+11:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//what-if-hospitals-ran-like-apple</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
<p>The experience of presenting to the Apple Store Genius Bar might carry some important lessons for hospital workflows. <em>Martin Seneviratne</em> explains why.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I recently had a technical problem with my Mac computer. It had been gradually slowing down and then one day it simply refused to turn on. The little spinning wheel just kept spinning ad infinitum. I consider myself to be reasonably tech savvy, so it was with a hint of defeat that I paid a visit to the Apple store.</p>

<p>After booking the appointment online, I arrived to be greeted by the iPad-wielding store managers, who directed me to a back desk where I would be seen by one of the Apple Geniuses. Meanwhile, they logged the serial number from underneath my computer to get a full record of exactly where that computer was sold, when it had been repaired, what Apple user IDs were associated with it. All of which appeared on my Genius? iPad when he arrived to help us.</p>

<p>The Genius turned out to be quite an eminent diagnostician. He took a history of the problem, asked about any previous issues I had experienced with the computer, and then began a very methodical series of investigations. He ran a script to check the integrity of the hardware, used an algorithm to detect logic errors in the software, checked the most recent internal error logs. The conclusion - a fatal software problem requiring a full reboot of the operating system.</p>

<p>At each step, he documented his findings in an electronic pro-forma built into an iPad app, which in the end generated a full report of the encounter for upload to Apple?s international database. Before he rebooted the system, I had to sign (with my finger on the iPad) an automatically-generated consent form. And when I left, with a software-refurbished Mac convalescing under my arm, I was emailed a complete summary.</p>

<p>At each step, he documented his findings in an electronic pro-forma built into an iPad app, which in the end generated a full report of the encounter for upload to Apple?s international database.</p>

<p>It struck me afterwards how medical this whole experience had been. My computer had basically come in GCS 3 on a background of chronic dementia with an acute deterioration. There was triage, investigations, diagnosis, intervention. And finally the computer was discharged. Yet it was all done with a level of slick technological efficiency that I had never seen in a hospital before. So the question naturally occurred - what if a hospital was run like an Apple store?</p>

<p>There are three aspects in particular of the <em>Apple model</em> that would be interesting to imagine in a healthcare context:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Bedside technology: In most hospitals, the average morning ward round could benefit significantly from some technological support. Currently so much time is wasted juggling different charts, deciphering illegible handwriting, running to check information on the computer. What we need is an iPad app with centralised patient information and a pro-forma interface for formulaic tasks like recording vitals, reporting examination findings and charting medications. This is precisely what Apple has already developed for computer maintenance.</p></li>
<li><p>Electronic records: Apple gives us aglimpse of what centralized e-health records might one day be. It has a global database where both devices and consumers are tracked with unique IDs, and information is synchronised across every Apple store internationally. That being said,concerns have been raised about the quantity of personal information held by Apple and the privacy regulations protecting it.</p></li>
<li><p>Staff training: Apple can monitor the time and outcome of each Genius consult and thus track the performance of each employee. This may seem overly intrusive, but imagine the potential efficiency gain if medical consults were electronically tracked and collectively analysed.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>Of course, we cannot model our entire healthcare system on an Apple store. There would not be very good patient follow-up, no personalised healthcare, and we would only treat people if they were still under warranty. And the hospital gift shop would have to expand considerably.</p>

<p>However, by leveraging technology to streamline routine tasks, Apple have designed an amazingly efficient ?computer healthcare? system from which the medical world can learn some valuable lessons.</p>

<p>The old mantra <em>an apple a day keeps the doctor away</em> almost implies a rivalry between doctors and apples. In fact, there should probably be more crosstalk.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>The Future of Pagers</title>
	  <link>//the-future-of-pagers</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-02-01T21:18:00+11:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//the-future-of-pagers</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Placeholder text test</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Gameifying Discharge Summaries</title>
	  <link>//gameifying-discharge-summaries</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-01-10T21:18:00+11:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//gameifying-discharge-summaries</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Placeholder text</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Digital Health Symposium</title>
	  <link>//digital-health-symposium</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-09T21:18:00+11:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//digital-health-symposium</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Placeholder text </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
