<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>jmodigital.com/</title>
   
   <link>http://jmodigital.com</link>
   <description>A network of training clinicians interested in digital health and entrepreneurship</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Martin Seneviratne</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>The Creative Destruction of Medicine by Eric Topol - a call to arms for innovators</title>
	  <link>//destruction-of-medicine</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-05-30T03:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//destruction-of-medicine</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
<p>How will the phenotype of a doctor change in a new health landscape dominated by technology?</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>The Creative Destruction of Medicine</em> sets out to examine the changing landscape as the digital revolution penetrates hospitals across the globe. As junior doctors we strive to provide the very best care for our patients, but all too often we find ourselves going to battle with inefficient systems and out-dated technologies. Most would agree that the health sector stands to gain enormously from the digital revolution, but for those on the ground the end-game remains elusive.</p>

<p><a href="https://exponential.singularityu.org/medicine/november-2013-faculty/eric-topol-md/">Eric Topol</a> is a leading voice on the digital transformation of healthcare. He is a cardiologist by training who has been ranked as one of the world’s top ten researchers. Formerly known for his role in questioning the cardiovascular safety of rofecoxib during the Voixx controversy, he is now the editor-in-chief of Medscape and director of the Scripps Translational Science Institute in California.</p>

<p>Topol begins with the provocative argument that medicine has become imprecise and wasteful as a result of our blind faith in randomised controlled trials. He believes that we apply research indiscriminately to individuals without trying to predict those who stand a gain a clinical benefit, the so-called ‘responders’. I was initially sceptical of his stab at the heart of evidence-based medicine. However, when confronted with data that as few as one in sixty people benefit from taking a <a href="http://www.thennt.com/nnt/statins-for-heart-disease-prevention-without-prior-heart-disease/">statin in primary prevention</a>, it does make you wonder whether shifting towards personalised medicine will sharpen our aim. While sequencing the human genome has not yet allowed us to cure genetic diseases, it can predict individuals with drug sensitivities. Perhaps using these tools will allow us to predict those who will benefit before reaching for our prescription pad, particularly given the onslaught of expensive monoclonals.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Will shifting towards personalised medicine sharpen our aim?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Computational power continues to increase exponentially in accordance with Moore’s law. The result has been the development of wireless remote sensors which integrate with smartphones and other wearable devices. Topol believes that sensors will improve the management of common medical conditions in real time. By transmitting this data to physicians, patients will no longer wait for an appointment to optimise management of their BP or BSL. Topol recalls his excitement when he received an email from a patient with an ECG monitor in his smartphone which read, “I’m in atrial fibrillation, what do I do now?” Health data stands to empower patients to become more involved in their own care.</p>

<p>Topol believes that these portable technologies will also change clinicians’ practice of medicine. He points to the availability of pocket-sized high-resolution ultrasounds. He believes these will become part of the physical exam and usurp the iconic, but rather primitive, stethoscope. I can imagine a world where doctors roam the wards with ultrasound probes attached to their smartphones ready to tackle difficult intravenous access, problematic ejection fractions or even troublesome gallstones. However, at thousands of dollars per ultrasound probe they remain cost prohibitive for most clinicians to integrate into their practice.</p>

<p>Technology will radically change how patients interact with their doctors according to Topol. In America, it takes two weeks to get an appointment with a primary care doctor, together with an average wait time of 60 minutes. But now, with the advent of remote monitoring and telemedicine, many of these consultations can occur remotely. And although GP appointments are more readily available in Australia, at least in the urban setting, this has not stopped the proliferation of <a href="https://www.qoctor.com.au">virtual medical clinics</a> offering to write medical certificates and make specialist referrals. The uberification of medical consultations has seen the proliferation of telemedicine and after-hours doctor services. These might just replace many traditional medical consultations. However, Australian patients continue to face hefty out-of-pocket fees for many of these services due to current Medicare billing regulations. Reform will be needed in order to compensate medical practitioners who provide care at a distance.</p>

<p>Next, Topol asks &quot;who should own the masses of patient data from sensors, genomic sequencing and laboratory tests?&quot;&quot; And what more logical answer than the patients themselves? Topol believes that the democratisation of medicine means that patients need to have ownership of their data. He is quick to counter paternalistic argument that medical data incites anxiety, quoting studies demonstrating that this is not the case. I agree that it is unnecessarily difficult for informed patients to access their laboratory tests and medical records. However, I wonder whether it is easier to argue for patient ownership of data in the US, where patients pay through health insurers, as opposed to Australia when tests are publically funded.</p>

<p>Topol also champions the development of transparent medical records. He references an <a href="https://www.opennotes.org">initiative</a> devised by Harvard graduates that allows patients access to their medical records requiring them to countersign alongside clinicians to verify their accuracy. They envisage a future where patients will be contributing to their own medical records! This seems to be a controversial concept when I pitch it to my colleagues. However, there is <a href="http://qualitysafety.bmj.com/content/early/2016/05/18/bmjqs-2015-004697">evidence</a> that open notes may improve patient satisfaction and benefit the doctor-patient relationship. Perhaps it also serves as a reminder of patient’s values when they diverge from those of the treating doctor.</p>

<p>You might wonder, what is the future of the hospital in this digital revolution? Topol believes that the hospital admissions in the future will be limited those undergoing surgical procedures or requiring intensive care. The majority of patients will be treated in the ambulatory setting with monitoring of vital signs using wireless sensors, point-of-care blood tests and daily consultation with remote clinicians. Many health systems are already making the shift towards providing a greater proportion of care in the outpatient setting. This is an attractive strategy to better deal with the epidemic of chronic disease whilst containing costs, creating efficiency and preventing the iatrogenic harms caused by the hospital system. </p>

<p>Topol concludes that the phenotype of a doctor will need to evolve for us to thrive in this newfound health landscape. This has implications for clinicians, educators and administrators alike. Topol has many ideas on how the digital revolution might change healthcare. Only time will tell which direction the industry will take. Either way, in the future of health the digital revolution will take centre stage. For those seeking an entrée to the revolution, this is the book for you. With countless opportunities for innovation, there’s never been a more exciting time to be a disruptive influence in health.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Australian Digital Health Ecosystem Survey</title>
	  <link>//digital-health-survey</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-04-14T03:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//digital-health-survey</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Across the digital health industry globally, there is so much innovation going on, it is hard to keep up. From across Australia, India, Europe and USA, I have been fortunate to meet a few of these entrepreneurs and work with a couple.</p>

<p>While there are a range of incubators, co-working spaces, accelerators, meetups, news sites, and communities that have popped up, my research on Australia&#39;s Digital Health Ecosystem shows a <em>significant gap</em> in what is publicly known. In the past few years I&#39;ve catalogued &#39;Australian-owned&#39; companies that I&#39;ve encountered in this field, and have a list of over 100 in this sector. Here&#39;s one of my graphs on the industry. It is obviously not a 100% capture of the industry due to my own limited reach.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Histogram.png" alt="Australian Digital Health" title="Digital health landscape in Australia"> </p>

<p>This graph concentrates on companies with <em>enabling</em> technologies rather than services, (ie. diet, education, exercise, outreach &amp; wellness programs are not included).</p>

<h3>The Ecosystem Data Gap</h3>

<p>I sought out to find what else is published on Australia’s Digital Health ecosystem and started at AusBiotech’s pages. Most companies on the directory are obviously pharma or biotech companies, consultancies, industry associations and universities. If you remove all the global (read non-Australian brands), you get a shortlist of a few actual Australian companies.</p>

<p>Looking at BiotechGate’s database, out of categories such as Pharma, Medical Device, Non-profit, Consulting, I selected what is usually an acronym for Digital Health (i.e. HealthTech). From the total 842 database of Australian companies, I found 41 Digital Health companies, and 63 MedTech companies. So a massive gap exists in ecosystem coverage.</p>

<p>There doesn’t seem to be a real reason for ‘Digital Health’ companies to be part of AusBiotech or MTAA. This could be that the value of this membership to small companies in this sector is not clear. It is also because these startups are accessing customer segments via channels that are new to the health industry. In fact, there is no strong ecosystem for digital health ventures to seed and grow in Australia.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I’ve also experienced the response from some industry executives that digital health is the ‘lesser’ industry. Is this true? Is it as simple as it seems? That it is just B2C, is not clinical, or is an easy mobile app.</p>

<p>Yes, Uber is also just a mobile app, and is simply killing the market in more industries than one, potentially to enter into healthcare soon. Such a response is well placed to kill fledgling digital health companies that could potentially become world-class platforms, that are highly scalable, covering geographies around the world and improving experience through a combination of analytics, health and devices.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Digital Health is any technology that digitises human, medical, biological, or health information. It&#39;s not just an app!</p>
</blockquote>

<h3>What is Digital Health?</h3>

<p>There is an FDA <a href="https://www.fda.gov/medicaldevices/digitalhealth/">definition</a>. However, I like to simplify it to “Digital Health as any technology that digitises human, medical, biological, or health information.”</p>

<p>It doesn’t matter if it leads to an educational product, a care service, a device with software, an analytics or research platform, a biomarker or genetic coding, an algorithm, a middleware integration tool, or an API. It is Digital Health. So if you’re still unsure, look no further than the reports on the industry from CBInsights, StartupHealth or RockHealth.</p>

<p>Yes, Cochlear implants, my friend, are a Digital Health product too :-)</p>

<h3>The Australian Digital Health Ecosystem Survey</h3>

<p>I embarked upon improving the digital health ecosystem a few years ago through HealthTech Sydney, doing over 26 industry seminars. I’m passionate about this space. This survey is to capture the current state of the ecosystem and publish it for general use. </p>

<p><em>If you are in Digital Health, I’d love to know you.</em> This is a comprehensive survey to understand the needs in this industry and how we can make it more successful. Your 3-5min will guide development of innovation capability in this industry.</p>

<h4>Survey: <a href="https://goo.gl/forms/IG3KbW17QtPeSyuq1">Australian Digital Health Company Survey</a></h4>

<p>Survey ends on May 24th. Results will be published on <a href="http://www.healthtechsydney.com.au/blog">HealthTech Sydney</a>, on LinkedIn and other related channels in June. You can subscribe to HealthTech Sydney <a href="http://eepurl.com/bQyhrD">here</a>.</p>

<p>Thanks!</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I am doing this survey as an independent evangelist in this industry.</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Lessons from leading a digital health innovation community</title>
	  <link>//health-innovation</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-11-01T03:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//health-innovation</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.healthtechsydney.com.au/">HealthTech Sydney</a> is a leading innovation community for healthcare technology that aims to improve education and accelerate commercialisation of ideas in healthcare. HealthTech Sydney connects players from research, medicine, biotechnology, and healthcare with technology, entrepreneurship, design and business to grow and support innovation in health.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4>The Why</h4>

<p>For nearly 3 years, I&#39;ve been leading a digital health innovation community named <a href="http://www.healthtechsydney.com.au/">HealthTech Sydney</a>. As a young biotech engineer in Australia, I worked on cochlear implant calibration and speech pathology software at the <a href="http://www.bionicsinstitute.org/Pages/default.aspx">Bionic Ear Institute</a>. However, there was no local network that made it easy to find mentors, active companies and problems to solve. It meant lack of career opportunities, and leaving health technology to work in finance for many years. But my passion has always been in healthcare, to develop innovative technologies into new products. So, I left one rewarding career and pivoted back to healthcare. I want to prevent this from happening to talented professionals who have a passion that is much needed in industries of the future, but lack opportunities for a rewarding scientific career.</p>

<h4>Healthcare &amp; Technology</h4>

<p>Australia is home to a deep scientific community and successful health companies like Resmed, Cochlear, Saluda Medical, Clarity Pharmaceuticals, Lorica Health, NeuClone, SpeeDx, Prospection, Precedence Healthcare and Osprey Medical to name just a few. However, successfully commercialising innovation is complex and requires combining multiple knowledge domains. The executives and scientists who have managed to create world-class companies have done it through great rigour, and often with little initial assistance or appreciation of their vision. Their experience is profound, and I believe it is crucial that their knowledge be applied to guide the paths of new entrants in the workforce, and design new business ideas that challenge incumbent models.</p>

<h4>Innovation in Digital Health</h4>

<p>Healthcare is a highly specialised industry with low levels of integration across services and solutions. The expectations of &#39;ready-to-go&#39; customer experience remains unfulfilled in healthcare services, not only for patients but also for many of the doctors and service providers in this field. This is changing with new niche solutions provided by companies that cater to the needs of specific patient groups, providing high quality of care and improving outcomes in a privately managed patient services ecosystem. This is the inception of creative upheaval in healthcare - by those who innovate despite the complexity.</p>

<p>We are in times of great change. Competitive forces birth new business solutions just as they render unadaptable ones to dust. Easily accessible technologies and impassioned entrepreneurs have overturned businesses in all sectors. Our careers span decades, geographies and now multiple industries. We need to remain on a continuous learning path. Healthcare is the latest one to feel the forces of innovative upheaval, and we need to keep up with the advances.</p>

<p>Reflecting on the difficulty of knowledge sharing in healthcare, a thriving community ecosystem needed development.</p>

<h4>The Importance of Communities</h4>

<p>A community fills the gap in an ecosystem where there is no supporting infrastructure to learn, engage and lead. It provides grassroots evidence of a need that precedes the development of a formal exchange or solution, either for knowledge or commerce. The gap is filled where the existing formal organisations do not cater for emerging customer segments, who have a different price point and use case. This exclusion occurs when the main avenue to learn and connect with like-minded professionals is via conferences that price out most people, or are not often enough to sustain an ecosystem.</p>

<p>A thirst for knowledge, connectivity and a shared vision to create positive change in the world is what sustains community groups. There are many people out there who want to put a &#39;dent in the universe&#39;, but lack a vehicle to help get them there. A vibrant community provides one such route.</p>

<hr>

<p>So, these are lessons I&#39;ve learnt from running HealthTech Sydney. I believe these principles can be applied in a variety of scenarios, companies, and organisations looking to seed ideas and build communities; from low-resource settings in developing countries, to corporates and incubators thinking about managing innovation groups, culture and new ideas. </p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Have a passionate vision:</strong> Your passion is infectious. It permeates the culture, attracting those with a similar vision to affect change. One of the main reasons I run HealthTech Sydney is to strive toward a vision of making Australia a major health-tech hub. This is also a core quality to seek in building the team around you, and to paraphrase <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joshtetrick">Josh Tetrick</a> (CEO, Hampton Creek), &quot;It&#39;s not hard to recruit the best people if your values and vision are to positively impact mankind.&quot; (Founder World 2015, SF)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Pick a pain point:</strong> Draw the attention of the community to a pain point that has driven health, technology, government or business conversations and strategic agendas. Talk to members to find out what keeps them up at night, what makes their jobs difficult, what patients care about, and what kills entrepreneur&#39;s business ideas and companies, or extirpates the potential impact of innovative research and technology. Addressing these pain points is crucial to improving innovation outcomes and realising the potential of serving unmet needs with relevant services. These conversations drive selection of the most pertinent topics that people care about and can rally behind.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Empower the community:</strong> I believe a community is a member-centric organisation that should provide maximum benefit to members for their patronage. The organisation is the channel that empowers members to achieve their objectives. In HeathTech Sydney, an aim has been to connect professionals and leverage the broad multi-disciplinary expertise in the group to achieve learning and innovation outcomes. The social, exploratory conversations in a community that uncover pain points also lead to discovering the expert knowledge and experience of your members. I&#39;ve learnt to ask more questions and listen more closely in the process.</p>

<p>In 2015, we held an event focusing on oncology clinical trial management that went into the frustrations and failures of managing this important stage for new drugs and devices. It was incredible to hear the accounts of Dr Ben Kong and Dr Vishal Gopal who manage oncology trials at a major Sydney hospital. Clinical trials for cancer may be international efforts that span hospitals in several countries. The difficulties are many, including understanding patient reaction to therapy, responding in timely fashion, cataloguing consistently and facilitating easy access to data. This was an incredible talk that kept attendees glued to their chairs (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c31F1De81UY&feature=youtu.be">videos</a>). I later discovered that <a href="https://www.flatiron.com/">Flatiron</a> (NY, USA) are working on a solution to just this global problem, providing validation of the relevance of the discussions.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Go deep on content:</strong> There is limited value in answering questions that are easily accessible, documented, or skin-deep in content. Real value comes from deep conversations that delve into a topic in great depth, and showcase solutions with multiple use-cases. Leverage expertise in innovative companies to talk about design considerations of developing their solutions to understand what works and what doesn&#39;t. These are often the most invaluable lessons in designing innovative products - the considerations and failures that others have been through. Challenge your assumptions and always ask &#39;why&#39; - don&#39;t accept things at face value.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Prepare and give your best knowledge:</strong> There is deep satisfaction in learning about trending topics and delving into the complexities of innovative businesses and technologies. There is greater satisfaction in sharing this with others. I learnt a lot of great concepts and frameworks during my MBA at <a href="http://www.ie.edu/business-school/the-school/rankings-recognition/">IE Business School</a> that I use in thinking about innovation, and that I wanted to share with others going through an explorative journey in strategy and technology.</p>

<p>However, if the objective is to be on the leading edge of news, innovation and technology, expect to be challenged. You need to do at least 3-5 hours of preparation to present in an engaging way for 5 min on a new topic. Share your best knowledge and spend time on preparation as this raises the quality and outcomes for everyone in the community. It also distinguishes your industry event from the numerous events readily available in cities most nights, and doesn&#39;t waste the time of attendees and speakers.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Build a great team:</strong> I&#39;m very thankful for the team and supporters who helped build HealthTech Sydney. I could not have delivered the quality and number of events without them. In the past three years, I went from almost single-handedly delivering seminars, to creating a team of four who have been critical in building and sustaining the community. In any enterprise, scale, consistency and quality requires dedication and teamwork. Building a great team requires training, establishing processes, building confidence, and constantly improving. If you want to create an innovation community, select people with broad skills but a shared passion. Establish tasks ownership, expectations of commitment, and help measure success. Communicate clearly, and celebrate together.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>I&#39;d like to acknowledge <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lissanthea">Lissanthea Taylor</a> for seeding the initial Meetup group in 2013. The group has expanded rapidly and there are now similar groups in Melbourne, Brisbane and Canberra. We welcome you to join us as we build our new platform - HealthTech Sydney.</p>

<p>In Part 2 of this article, I will share the remaining lessons and provide some updates on the vision ahead. I look forward to hearing your experiences in building communities.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
