<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>jmodigital.com/</title>
   
   <link>http://jmodigital.com</link>
   <description>A network of training clinicians interested in digital health and entrepreneurship</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Martin Seneviratne</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>A prescription to change</title>
	  <link>//eprescribing</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-04-22T20:18:00+10:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//eprescribing</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>A funny thing happened the other day that made me think I was back in the last century.</p>

<p>My son was holidaying with friends about four hours from home, and had a recurrence of his atopic eczema. Unfortunately he had forgotten his topical steroid, so I organised the dispensing of the medicine through a pharmacy, local to where he was staying.</p>

<p>Firstly the pharmacist requested me to fax the script but, as I had disposed of my last fax machine in 1993, this was not possible. I asked if I could email the script and fortunately the pharmacist agreed, though I do not believe it was particularly secure. All was well until at the end of our conversation when I was reminded to send the original script to the pharmacy. At this point I realised we are so far away from true digital healthcare.</p>

<p>So I did a lot of research into this matter and realised that there is both State and Commonwealth legislation governing the dispensing of medicines. Looking at these documents, a valid prescription must be on paper, in the medical practitioner&#39;s own handwriting using indelible ink, signed and dated. There are mandatory details including the medical practitioner&#39;s name, address and phone number (NO need for prescriber number), the patient&#39;s name and address (NO need for the date of birth), and details about the medicine. Oh, and by the way this can be written on a serviette from the local coffee shop as there are no specifications on the paper to be used. Personally I am wondering if a chiselled stone tablet would be acceptable!</p>

<p>You might ask why I did not use the computer to write the script. Well I am an Emergency Physician, and at my home I cannot afford to purchase practice software that has electronic prescribing capability. There is no alternative! Even if I did manage to order the medicine electronically, I would still have to print the script, sign it, scan it, email it, and then send it through the mail.</p>

<p>In my mind I envisaged using my computer to access a secure server with secondary code certification (via my phone), enter the appropriate prescription details and send the script through to a &#39;pharmacy cloud&#39; with a message my son a QR code. He could then go into any pharmacy, have the QR code scanned, and the pharmacist could confidently dispense the medicine following confirmation of his identity. </p>

<p>There is a long way to go before we have a safer, and more simple system for prescribing medicines for patients and unfortunately the road is tortuous, as it includes changing legislation involving the Commonwealth and all State governments. But it is journey that we must take to improve the quality and safety of care to our patients.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Tablet-based health interventions</title>
	  <link>//ehealth-initiatives-orange</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-04-13T20:18:00+10:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//ehealth-initiatives-orange</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Following Martin&#39;s <a href="/what-if-hospitals-ran-like-apple">article</a> last month comparing the genius bar at Apple to a clinicians diagnostic algorithm, it&#39;s appropriate to bring to light the recent e-prospects of Orange Health Service. Never mind that we may be 4 hours into the wild western NSW; the new Orange Hospital, which was completed in 2011, is at the forefront of enthusiasm for innovation in medical technology. </p>

<p>I may be speaking for a select few, or perhaps the niche personality types of JMOs, but I feel that in today&#39;s society, the marriage of slight OCD traits and a digital addiction result in an aggressive intolerance to inefficiency.  These first-world frustrations are exemplified by the fact that we live in a digital world, yet once you walk through the doors of a hospital, you are entering the mid 90s.  A boss tells a registrar a job, who then tells the junior, who then writes that job on a piece of paper, who then completes the job, only to then contact the registrar who then contacts the boss to confirm the job has been completed. It seems comical, not to mention the safety issues and discrepancies of the Chinese-whispers style communication, or the daily issue of JMOs dropping their lists in the carpark, leaving them at the local cafe, or even worse, in the toilet.</p>

<p>In 2015 the Orange executive launched a Dragon&#39;s Den competition that enabled JMOs to contribute their ideas to a panel and be awarded funding for small projects. JMOs in OHS proposed 2 concepts: iPads on the wards for task allocation, and the creation of more medical apps. We proposed to equip ward based JMOs with tablets loaded with an application for task management, which is securely backed up and replaced the need for paper lists. The concept is that nursing and allied staff will have access to this list, and can add tasks as appropriate. </p>

<p>The power of this solution is in reliability - paper lists and the use of either whiteboards or informal verbal handover of tasks leads to many mistakes. Furthermore, transitioning to an electronic format might also help remedy our perhaps pathological 21st century aversion to inefficiencies. </p>

<p>But it doesn&#39;t end there. Imagine the potential for patient education. DrawMD - a well used app in the US - could allow a cardiologist to explain atherosclerosis to patients with diagrams, or allow a patient to view their angiogram results at the bedside with the physician explaining. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/drawMD.jpg" alt="Cardiologist explaining concept to a patient using DrawMD" title="DrawMD"></p>

<p>By way of example, in 2015 OneView launched a tablet-based patient portal in Epworth Eastern Hospital, Melbourne. Their nurse rounding application has resulted in a 6% decrease in pressure ulcers and a 4% decrease in patient falls. Meanwhile patients prepare for discharge with video education, goal completion and real-time collaboration with their care teams, resulting in 6% decrease in length of stay. [1]</p>

<p>You are probably thinking: this all sounds fairly simple! And not exactly ground breaking... However there are critical barriers in terms of change management and data security that need to be overcome. But can the medical world really resist this digital storm?</p>

<hr>

<p><sub><em>[1] Kinmont, K. Epworth Eastern Hospital Realises Improved Outcomes with Oneview Interactive Patient Care Technology Solutions. Oct 21, 2015. News, Available from; Oneview Blog: http://www.oneviewhealthcare.com/epworth-improved-outcomes/</em></sub></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>What if hospitals were run by Apple</title>
	  <link>//what-if-hospitals-ran-like-apple</link>
	  <author>Martin Seneviratne</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-02-01T21:18:00+11:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//what-if-hospitals-ran-like-apple</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
<p>The experience of presenting to the Apple Store Genius Bar might carry some important lessons for hospital workflows. <em>Martin Seneviratne</em> explains why.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I recently had a technical problem with my Mac computer. It had been gradually slowing down and then one day it simply refused to turn on. The little spinning wheel just kept spinning ad infinitum. I consider myself to be reasonably tech savvy, so it was with a hint of defeat that I paid a visit to the Apple store.</p>

<p>After booking the appointment online, I arrived to be greeted by the iPad-wielding store managers, who directed me to a back desk where I would be seen by one of the Apple Geniuses. Meanwhile, they logged the serial number from underneath my computer to get a full record of exactly where that computer was sold, when it had been repaired, what Apple user IDs were associated with it. All of which appeared on my Genius? iPad when he arrived to help us.</p>

<p>The Genius turned out to be quite an eminent diagnostician. He took a history of the problem, asked about any previous issues I had experienced with the computer, and then began a very methodical series of investigations. He ran a script to check the integrity of the hardware, used an algorithm to detect logic errors in the software, checked the most recent internal error logs. The conclusion - a fatal software problem requiring a full reboot of the operating system.</p>

<p>At each step, he documented his findings in an electronic pro-forma built into an iPad app, which in the end generated a full report of the encounter for upload to Apple?s international database. Before he rebooted the system, I had to sign (with my finger on the iPad) an automatically-generated consent form. And when I left, with a software-refurbished Mac convalescing under my arm, I was emailed a complete summary.</p>

<p>At each step, he documented his findings in an electronic pro-forma built into an iPad app, which in the end generated a full report of the encounter for upload to Apple?s international database.</p>

<p>It struck me afterwards how medical this whole experience had been. My computer had basically come in GCS 3 on a background of chronic dementia with an acute deterioration. There was triage, investigations, diagnosis, intervention. And finally the computer was discharged. Yet it was all done with a level of slick technological efficiency that I had never seen in a hospital before. So the question naturally occurred - what if a hospital was run like an Apple store?</p>

<p>There are three aspects in particular of the <em>Apple model</em> that would be interesting to imagine in a healthcare context:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Bedside technology: In most hospitals, the average morning ward round could benefit significantly from some technological support. Currently so much time is wasted juggling different charts, deciphering illegible handwriting, running to check information on the computer. What we need is an iPad app with centralised patient information and a pro-forma interface for formulaic tasks like recording vitals, reporting examination findings and charting medications. This is precisely what Apple has already developed for computer maintenance.</p></li>
<li><p>Electronic records: Apple gives us aglimpse of what centralized e-health records might one day be. It has a global database where both devices and consumers are tracked with unique IDs, and information is synchronised across every Apple store internationally. That being said,concerns have been raised about the quantity of personal information held by Apple and the privacy regulations protecting it.</p></li>
<li><p>Staff training: Apple can monitor the time and outcome of each Genius consult and thus track the performance of each employee. This may seem overly intrusive, but imagine the potential efficiency gain if medical consults were electronically tracked and collectively analysed.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>Of course, we cannot model our entire healthcare system on an Apple store. There would not be very good patient follow-up, no personalised healthcare, and we would only treat people if they were still under warranty. And the hospital gift shop would have to expand considerably.</p>

<p>However, by leveraging technology to streamline routine tasks, Apple have designed an amazingly efficient ?computer healthcare? system from which the medical world can learn some valuable lessons.</p>

<p>The old mantra <em>an apple a day keeps the doctor away</em> almost implies a rivalry between doctors and apples. In fact, there should probably be more crosstalk.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
